
<doc sysid="ref" docid="bbc.242436" genre="news" origlang="en" topic="politics">
<p>
<seg id="1">Russia's Putin sacks chief of staff Sergei Ivanov</seg>
<seg id="2">Russian President Vladimir Putin has unexpectedly dismissed his chief of staff Sergei Ivanov.</seg>
<seg id="3">Mr Ivanov has been part of Mr Putin's trusted inner circle for many years.</seg>
<seg id="4">The 63-year-old has now been made a special representative for environmental and transport issues.</seg>
<seg id="5">A statement from the Kremlin said that Mr Putin had "decreed to relieve Ivanov of his duties as head of the Russian presidential administration," but gave no reason.</seg>
<seg id="6">Mr Ivanov's deputy since 2012, Anton Vaino, has been appointed as his successor.</seg>
<seg id="7">Mr Vaino, 44, is a former diplomat.</seg>
<seg id="8">Born in the Estonian capital Tallinn in 1972, he graduated from the prestigious Moscow State Institute of International Relations (MGIMO) and served in the Tokyo embassy.</seg>
<seg id="9">Later he managed presidential protocol and government staff, the Kremlin website says (in Russian).</seg>
<seg id="10">On being appointed, he told Mr Putin: "Thank you for your trust."</seg>
<seg id="11">I think the administration's most important task is to support your activity as head of state in terms of drafting laws and control over how your instructions are implemented.</seg>
<seg id="12">Mr Putin told a Russian TV station on Friday that Mr Ivanov had asked to leave the post, and recommended that Mr Vaino should replace him.</seg>
<seg id="13">Do the smiles convince?</seg>
<seg id="14">This is a move that has mystified Moscow.</seg>
<seg id="15">Sergei Ivanov has long been one of Vladimir Putin's closest allies and, like him, served in the Soviet security service, the KGB.</seg>
<seg id="16">As chief of staff he was one of the most powerful men in the country.</seg>
<seg id="17">In a meeting with President Putin shown on state television both men claimed that the chief of staff was stepping down at his own request.</seg>
<seg id="18">But despite the smiles for the cameras, few here are convinced - especially now, just before parliamentary elections.</seg>
<seg id="19">So is this the fall-out from some kind of power struggle?</seg>
<seg id="20">No-one knows yet.</seg>
<seg id="21">But the official claim - that a man once touted as a potential president, suddenly wanted to run Russia's environmental policy - has been met with great scepticism.</seg>
<seg id="22">In remarks to Mr Putin, quoted on the Kremlin website, Mr Ivanov said "it's true that in early 2012 I asked you, in a conversation, to entrust me with this very complicated post, even - you could say - troublesome post, for four years.</seg>
<seg id="23">Well, it turns out that I've been presidential chief of staff for four years and eight months.</seg>
<seg id="24">Mr Ivanov took up the post in December 2011.</seg>
<seg id="25">He served previously as a deputy prime minister and defence minister.</seg>
<seg id="26">He is a member of the Russian Security Council and a former member of the KGB state security service, like Mr Putin.</seg>
<seg id="27">In the late 1990s, when Mr Putin was head of the Federal Security Service (FSB), which replaced the KGB, Mr Ivanov was appointed as his deputy.</seg>
<seg id="28">When Mr Putin came to power, he named Mr Ivanov as one of the five people he trusted most.</seg>
<seg id="29">It was once thought that Mr Ivanov might become president of Russia after Mr Putin's second term, as a third term for Mr Putin would have been unconstitutional.</seg>
<seg id="30">But that post was taken by another close Putin ally, Dmitry Medvedev.</seg>
<seg id="31">Mr Putin became prime minister, before returning to the presidency just three-and-a-half years later.</seg>
</p>
</doc>
