
<doc sysid="ref" docid="augsburger-allgemeine.de.44740" genre="news" origlang="de" topic="society">
<p>
<seg id="1">Seeking refuge: "Every refugee woman has dealt with sexual violence"</seg>
<seg id="2">For women fleeing a country on their own, sexual violence is almost part of daily life.</seg>
<seg id="3">When they arrive in Germany, they are often traumatised.</seg>
<seg id="4">One house offers refuge.</seg>
<seg id="5">Four women are sitting in a large kitchen.</seg>
<seg id="6">Every one of them has a baby with them, the oldest of which is one year old.</seg>
<seg id="7">One woman holds her little son in her arms.</seg>
<seg id="8">He looks around the room inquisitively, his eyes wide.</seg>
<seg id="9">His mother stares at the tabletop.</seg>
<seg id="10">Until she realises she's being watched.</seg>
<seg id="11">She smiles briefly and kisses the child.</seg>
<seg id="12">The scene looks normal.</seg>
<seg id="13">Until you start talking to Katrin Bahr.</seg>
<seg id="14">She is the field manager for Condrobs, a provider of social assistance within Bavaria. One of the issues she deals with is refugee women.</seg>
<seg id="15">The four women in the kitchen are refugees.</seg>
<seg id="16">They live in the north of Munich, in one of the few decentralised accommodation centres in Bavaria for refugee women and their children who have made the journey alone.</seg>
<seg id="17">Condrobs opened the centre in January, in collaboration with Pro Familia and the Munich Women's Help organisation.</seg>
<seg id="18">It recently had its official opening.</seg>
<seg id="19">60 people live there - around 40 women and 20 children.</seg>
<seg id="20">There are no men - not even male visitors.</seg>
<seg id="21">The exception is a bodyguard on the door.</seg>
<seg id="22">"I'm not exaggerating when I say that every woman who arrives here has dealt with sexual violence on her way to find refuge," said Bahr.</seg>
<seg id="23">"Men flee because of war, because they are politically persecuted, because they are threatened with torture or death, or because their families pin their hopes on them and send them to Europe," she explains.</seg>
<seg id="24">When women flee, other reasons are in the foreground: "Many women sneak away secretly, because they see no other way out".</seg>
<seg id="25">In their home countries, they experienced sexual violence, forced marriage, honour killings, slavery or forced prostitution.</seg>
<seg id="26">That propels them forward.</seg>
<seg id="27">And it continues even while they're on the run.</seg>
<seg id="28">"It is not a rare occurrence that traffickers request a sexual act in exchange for a bottle of water, for example," says Bahr.</seg>
<seg id="29">And the woman are alone, unprotected by their families.</seg>
<seg id="30">If you think that this stops as soon as they arrive in Germany, you'd be wrong, says Bahr.</seg>
<seg id="31">Even in Germany, lone women are often seen as inferior in refugee accommodation, and, in the worst cases, they are abused.</seg>
<seg id="32">As a result, around 90 percent of the women living in accommodation in the north of Munich are traumatised, she estimates.</seg>
<seg id="33">"Some of the children were certainly not conceived with the woman's consent".</seg>
<seg id="34">Many women are so used to it that they do not say anything, she says.</seg>
<seg id="35">"Or they can't bring themselves to talk about what they experienced because they are too ashamed".</seg>
<seg id="36">Because they often don't know how to get help, there needs to be more accommodation just for them, says Bahr.</seg>
<seg id="37">In Bavaria, the seven district governments are responsible for providing accommodation for refugees.</seg>
<seg id="38">When asked if they knew of projects like the one in Munich operating within the areas they covered, some answered with "no".</seg>
<seg id="39">In Upper Palatinate and Upper Franconia regions, for example, there is no similar accommodation offered by the government.</seg>
<seg id="40">Even in Swabia, women who come as lone refugees are not given separate accommodation, says Karl-Heinz Meyer, press spokesperson for the region.</seg>
<seg id="41">In Upper Bavaria, Lower Franconia and Middle Franconia, floors, or individual houses, are set aside in some shared accommodation for lone women and their children.</seg>
<seg id="42">The exception is Lower Bavaria: there, there are two central accommodation centres exclusively for women.</seg>
<seg id="43">Even the European Parliament's Committee on "Women's Rights and Gender Equality" stresses that women must be provided with accommodation separate from that of the men.</seg>
<seg id="44">In a study published on behalf of the Committee, it was stated that "it is very important that men and women are given separate accommodation."</seg>
<seg id="45">"If there is a lack of private space, or if men and women are provided with accommodation together, this can result in (perpetual) violence against women".</seg>
<seg id="46">Washing facilities, above all, should be separate, and easily accessible for women, according to the study.</seg>
<seg id="47">The extent to which women need this protection can be seen in the sheer number of people interested in the house in Munich.</seg>
<seg id="48">"Since word has got around that we exist, we have developed a long waiting list," says Bahr.</seg>
<seg id="49">It would be easy to open a second house.</seg>
</p>
</doc>
