
<doc sysid="ref" docid="cbsnews.146271" genre="news" origlang="en" topic="society,other">
<p>
<seg id="1">Mother of 6-year-old with microcephaly: "It gets better"</seg>
<seg id="2">Like most six-year-olds, Edmund Picciuto loves singing, toys and, of course, his mother.</seg>
<seg id="3">But unlike most of his peers, Edmund has microcephaly, the result of a genetic disorder his mom Elizabeth Picciuto didn't know about while pregnant.</seg>
<seg id="4">When he first came home my initial thought was, I can't do this.</seg>
<seg id="5">I can't do this.</seg>
<seg id="6">I didn't sign up for this.</seg>
<seg id="7">Which is not true at all -- of course you sign up for it," she said.</seg>
<seg id="8">She and her husband, Vincent, were told Edmund might never recognize them, and that he might not even survive.</seg>
<seg id="9">Some doctors went as far as suggesting he be institutionalized.</seg>
<seg id="10">"My first response was 'I didn't think people did that anymore,'" Picciuto explained.</seg>
<seg id="11">Edmund walks with the help of a walker.</seg>
<seg id="12">Edmund didn't sit up or crawl until he was three, and he still doesn't talk.</seg>
<seg id="13">But he's slowly meeting some milestones.</seg>
<seg id="14">He's walking with help, and riding a bike.</seg>
<seg id="15">He also loves playing with his two brothers, and singing.</seg>
<seg id="16">Elizabeth demonstrates the sign language Edmund made up for "please sing to me."</seg>
<seg id="17">"We're teaching him sign language," Picciuto told CBS News.</seg>
<seg id="18">But it's not just typical sign language -- she says Edmund has invented some of his own signs.</seg>
<seg id="19">Microcephaly can arise from a number of different conditions: genetic ones like Edmund's, and infections during pregnancy from viruses like measles and Zika.</seg>
<seg id="20">Symptoms and prognosis can vary widely.</seg>
<seg id="21">It's too early to tell how it will affect the lives of those infected with Zika.</seg>
<seg id="22">Picciuto remembers the emotional toll of an uncertain future.</seg>
<seg id="23">I kept saying, what's going to happen?</seg>
<seg id="24">What's going to happen?</seg>
<seg id="25">And she still doesn't really know.</seg>
<seg id="26">I actually haven't asked for a prognosis in forever, because I don't expect anyone to really be able to tell me.</seg>
<seg id="27">But Picciuto has hopeful advice for the mothers of babies with birth defects from Zika.</seg>
<seg id="28">It gets better.</seg>
<seg id="29">You know it will get better for you.</seg>
<seg id="30">You will love your child, and your child will love you.</seg>
</p>
</doc>
